Software Engineering Radio episode 4,
scripting languages.
Welcome to this episode of Software
Engineering Radio. This time Alex and
Marcus will talk about scripting
languages. So, to get us started, I
think Alex, could you explain what are
scripting languages are and why they're
such a hype today? Well, what scripting
languages are is actually one of the
toughest question I guess because it's
not that clearly defined.
A lot of people think
scripting languages doesn't mean it's
interpreted because it was that way in
the earlier days of computing. There
were the compiler languages and
on the other other hand there were the
interpreted languages, the scripting
languages. But that is not true anymore
for a long time. I mean basic is
interpreted, Java if you want is
interpreted.
Yeah, to some extent. Yeah, of course
the more modern scripting languages like
Ruby can be compiled too. So, that's not
the criteria that's true today anymore.
Okay. If you look at Wikipedia they say
scripting languages are for short and
easy tasks. They are or they lack
features that are necessary for huge
projects with a lot of people like type
safety. I guess we can talk a bit on
this later on.
Yes. They have implicit variable
declaration which is not a good criteria
anymore. C# in the next version will
have implicit variable declaration too.
Scripting languages have dynamic type
conversion and automatic memory
management. So, the Wikipedia definition
is not bad but not so good too because
there are a lot of counter examples for
all of this. So, I guess the the
definition is pretty fuzzy right now.
My definition of scripting languages is
pretty close to the Wikipedia
definition. Scripting languages are
usually designed to make programming
easier. So, they are more
human-centered, not so much designed to
make it easy to be compiled or
interpreted by the machine. It's they
are readable. Simplicity is a huge
design principle in most scripting
languages. You usually need a lot less
code to program the same stuff
compared to Java or C++ or the other
languages. Dynamic typing garbage
collection actually are core features of
most scripting languages
and another point is scripting languages
are often designed for specific domain.
So, would you say that scripting
languages are are typically domain
specific?
Typically,
maybe yes. Not not all of them. Right,
because you Ruby A language like Ruby is
pretty
yeah, you can use it for anything you
want.
But nevertheless, a lot of scripting
languages look at PHP. It's it's has a
main focus on web development. So, yes,
they are often domain specific. Although
just to clarify for our listeners, you
shouldn't confuse these domain specific
languages we talk about here like being
domain specific for web page
development, you shouldn't confuse them
with DSLs in the sense of model driven
development.
Yeah, for sure not. That's a huge
difference. Just maybe another historic
point in the programming language
community, there has been a long
discussion about writability versus
readability. So, that means you should
be able to write programs quickly but
maybe not be able to read them easily
afterwards. For example, if you look at
APL, the the the pro the numeric
processing language which is very
concise you but you can never ever read
your programs again. That's not the
focus of scripting languages, is it?
Yeah,
actually you could argue that Pearl has
the same problem.
Yes, okay, but that's a very old
scripting language. Yeah. So, the newer
ones like Ruby or Python or or Ruby
don't have these problems. Yeah.
Okay.
You mentioned before
scripting languages are simpler to to
use. So, does it mean they're
incomplete? I mean, is it you know, is
it hard to do complex things with them
or
because just because they're simple?
No, for sure not.
This is the Wikipedia definition. I'm
not so
I'm not feeling good about this
definition actually because you can
program anything you want with most of
the scripting languages
maybe besides some stuff like system
level software or drive like drivers or
stuff like that or embedded software.
Most of the other things you can
actually do with scripting languages
that they are
most of them are complete programming
languages
and if you look at the examples where
they are used
you you can see that it's like that.
It's not an incomplete language. It's
not a a toy language or something like
that. Ruby on Rails is is which is a
framework to do three-tier web
applications with Ruby which is a
scripting language
is a complete system for for writing
really complex web applications. A lot
of the web shops you actually use day by
day are written in one or another
scripting language. So, that's not
it's not an incomplete feature set or
something like that. But is there a kind
of hotspot? Are there typical kinds of
applications that are built with
scripting languages and are there other
kinds of applications you wouldn't
recommend them for? Let's
first elaborate on the what I wouldn't
use it for.
Actually, I
have some kind well, a little problem
seeing huge really huge projects with
200 people working on it doing
being done in a scripting language.
That's not the hotspot right now.
Doesn't mean it will not because if you
look at Ruby it's conceptual on a level
like Smalltalk. So, it's all there.
Nevertheless, it's not done often and
there are some pitfalls you you have to
address like dynamic typing. The typical
usages are shell script replacement.
That's the classic point.
That's where they come from actually.
Stuff like build environments are often
done in scripting languages.
A lot of web development is done in
scripting languages. I would say that
more web development is done in
scripting languages right now than in
the the more serious
languages like Java or C#. Also, if you
look at a Linux distribution, there are
tons of small GUI programs written in
Tcl/Tk. So, there's there's a hotspot
too for scripting languages. Is there
anything you could say about the team
size? I mean, you already mentioned that
you wouldn't do a project with 200
people. Is that is that a problem of the
language or is it a problem of
you wouldn't find enough developers for
those kinds of languages today?
It's a bit difficult
finding developers for the languages
because like I said, PHP is really huge.
There are a lot of people out there that
do PHP on a daily basis. So, there's a
huge pool of script developers.
Nevertheless,
it's not so much used in huge projects
and
I wouldn't say professional developers
are harder to find for scripting
languages because of course they do
professional stuff there.
It's hard to say. I don't think it's
it's a problem of finding people
actually. There are some features of
scripting languages that make it tough
to to do huge projects. Same like like
Smalltalk you might argue. Dynamic
typing is is a thing you have to
address. You have to do a lot of more
unit tests for example to address
dynamic typing problems that might occur
in huge teams. So,
huge team is a is a problem I guess for
for most of the scripting languages
right now. Something I'd like to point
out is that today when when developing
software for example, if you look at
Java, the most important thing actually
isn't the language anymore one could
argue. Instead, it's the frameworks.
Yeah. If somebody has to learn Java
today, learning the language is easy but
understanding all this J2EE or JEE stuff
as it's now called, learning all that
stuff and and being proficient there and
using the right patterns and the right
idioms, that's really hard.
Yeah, you're right.
On the other hand, on the other hand I
think a good language cannot be
compensated with with good frameworks
because for example if you look at Java
as a as a counter example for good
language
if if you want to
associate a piece of behavior with a
button or with another event, you have
to typically write an inner class that
implements some kind of interface and
then implement some execute operation
all that. So, you basically have to
implement the command pattern writing
five or six lines of code just to get
your real business logic somewhere. If
you have a scripting languages with code
blocks or closures in general, this is
usually just a curly brace
and a vertical bar and a couple of
functional business logic statements.
So, you can express things much more
concisely and certain features such as
closures are really important to build
good frameworks. So, you cannot really
compensate a good language with a huge
amount of frameworks.
You you so right on this point. If you
look at a framework and it's more like
than a framework actually. Nevertheless,
if you look at Ruby on Rails,
I don't think anyone from the Java
community
would have come up with an idea and in a
concept like Ruby on Rails. Of course,
you can do copies that are close to Ruby
on Rails.
and they're doing those continuation
servers right now in Java.
exactly. So,
you can copy the concept and you can get
close, but it doesn't feel the same way.
So, yes, the language has a huge effect
on the framework.
Another interesting point there is the
scripting languages actually do have
huge amount of libraries, they call
them,
for
where you can find functionality for
nearly anything you want or can can
think of. So,
Pearl and Python have huge libraries in
the back.
Okay, so maybe just to to continue that
point you made before that scripting
languages are often used for shell
script replacement. Why should I do
that? I mean, aren't the shell languages
good enough? I'm not a Linux guy, Unix
guy, so I don't really know. So, why
would you do that? Well, actually the
modern shells are pretty powerful. If
you look at Bash or TC shell, then they
are huge. They you can do anything you
want with them, but they are not very
it's tough to to work with them
sometimes.
If you want to debug them, that's all
not so easy to do.
But the main point for the scripting
languages actually is
they are more platform independent. You
can use a Pearl script on or if you do
it right or with the
that you want to to do it in that way.
You can use a Pearl script on Unix and
you can use it on Windows
without a problem. So, they are more
platform independent than
normal Bash or TC shell scripts are. The
programming concepts usually are
more powerful to you have object
orientation for example,
some kinds of functional programming.
So, they are they are more high-level
programming constructs in there.
And therefore, they are a lot easier to
program.
For example, if you want to do a build
script or a build environment for huge
project, that can be pretty complex. So,
doing this with Bash is
can be a pain at least. So,
they have an edge there.
I have even heard of people who say that
instead of building your in the Java
world, instead of building your build
scripts with Ant, you should use Ruby
because that makes things much easier
than all those curly braces these these
angle brackets and all that stuff.
Yeah, one
huge advantage there is you are not
stuck with the declarative type. Ant,
you have a just a declarative type of
declaring what you want to build and
what are the dependencies.
When you do it with Ruby, you can
program anything you want in this
script. So,
there's no limit there. Yeah, that's
that's actually true because if you want
to do like conditionals in Ant and do
something only in certain circumstances,
that's really a pain. I mean, that
doesn't that's not Another point is
with scripting languages, you can do
more complex or complicated even stuff
there too. You have GUI libraries, you
can do networking stuff using web
services, whatever you need. So, you're
not limited actually.
The next point is something that maybe
everybody thinks about when thinking
about scripting languages, are they
slow?
That's complicated
too.
They they don't have to be slow. That's
that's the first point. Actually,
there's nothing in the concept that
makes them slow. So, it's it's more of
implementation problems sometimes or uh
Yeah, it's it's not really a conceptual
problem. Nevertheless, right now it's
that way that most of the scripting
languages are a bit slower than the
native well, native compiled languages
like C or C++ or so on. So,
yes, usually they are a bit slower. Of
course, this doesn't have to be a
problem. Nevertheless, it's a fact.
Usually not a problem that they're a bit
slower. If you don't do number
crunching, then that usually doesn't
matter because the bottleneck is the
network or the database or whatever.
Yeah. And if you look at the design
principles of Ruby, the creator of Ruby
always said it's more important to make
the
language easy to use, easy to read, and
not performance or faster. That's not
the main focus of scripting languages
usually. So, if you if they have to make
a trade-off there, they usually decide
against faster as option.
Yeah, I mean, and that means as a
consequence that maybe as we said
before, you wouldn't use a scripting
languages to develop embedded automotive
software that controls your your your
the burning process in your engine. So,
that's not the the target or the the
typical domain. Yeah, and for the other
stuff like web shops or things like
that, it's also not a problem actually
to to use a scripting language because
usually network or database are limiting
factors there. So,
pure CPU power isn't that important in
this domain usually.
Right. Yeah. And of course, I mean, in
the end it's always the same. If you
want additional flexibility and
reflection and dynamic this and dynamic
that, then you pay a price. Yeah. It's
always the same. Yeah, another point
there is
a lot of scripting languages get ported
to standard
yeah, virtual machines like Java virtual
machine or .NET runtime. So,
they use approaches the other languages
use too and get performance benefits
from that. It's it's not easy. It's it's
a lot of work there, but it also helps
performance a lot.
So, so how important is it for the
for the popularity of scripting
languages that they can be run on
mainstream VMs such as the Java VM or
the .NET common language which runtime?
Mhm. I think it's a it's a huge point to
get them on these platforms. If you have
a tight integration with
Groovy for example in Java, you can do a
lot of fancy stuff. You can call Java
classes from Groovy. You can write unit
tests with Groovy testing Java classes
and backwards of course. So, that's
that's a huge point for
things you can do with scripting
languages besides the performance point.
So, does does that mean that if we I
mean, if we use a scripting language
language on Java and can reuse all the
libraries like JTB and stuff, that still
doesn't mean that the frameworks are
kind of built with the scripting
language in mind. So, you it doesn't it
really doesn't feel exactly like like I
don't know like like Ruby on Rails.
Still Java with a little bit of
syntactic sugar, right?
Exactly. That's why the Groovy people do
yeah, develop their own frameworks right
now. They they do their frameworks with
a Groovy spirit in it parallel to the
Java stuff. So,
you're so right. That's that's a huge
point there. Okay. Mhm. Not sure if this
is the right way to go either. So, we
have Java EE and then we have Java
Groovy EE. I don't know. Well, I'm I'm
not sure. I guess it
the better solution will win there. And
if we are if we stuck to Java, whatever
that means, because I don't think Java
is as bad as most people say right now.
So, nevertheless, if we stuck with Java,
we we might lose some advantages of the
scripting
power and maybe we have to at least we
have the possibility to combine them and
use the best of both sides. So, it's
about choice, I guess.
Yeah, some people argue that the the
phase where Java is the motor of the
innovation is already kind of gone. I
think it wasn't it Bruce Eckel who wrote
this book Beyond Java or who was it?
Bruce Tate, I guess. Bruce Tate, I don't
know. I have the book lying around
somewhere here. So, that kind of shows
that some people think that the the the
the phase where Java is really the the
language for the really creative people
is over and that they move to languages
like Ruby. Yes, I think so, too.
It's pretty obvious if you read the
weblogs right now.
The there most of the
people that are very noisy at least
switch over to to Ruby right now from
the Java community.
But I I guess it's also a bit of
well, a Gartner would call it hype cycle
thing. Yeah, of course. Ruby is great,
but Java is not that bad either. So, you
have to use the right tool for the
problem you have, I guess. Yeah. Yeah.
And and maybe just to to to to conclude
this this this section about, you know,
mainstream VMs and and scripting
languages, Java will provide a better
integration for scripting languages in
the future. The the JSR 223 uh
deals with better integration of
scripting languages into Java 6. That
will probably to be Java 6. And Groovy
is not the only Java scripting language
to to just mention here. There's
BeanShell which has been there for for I
guess years at least
at least 3 years. I don't know.
For a long time right now,
which is pretty popular. Mhm. And if you
look at BeanShell,
one feature is used that you get from
this integration,
you can use it as an automation
automation language for your
applications actually. You can embed
BeanShell in your program to
make yeah, automation automation of your
program possible.
Okay.
Huge feature.
Okay, so so if we look at scripting
languages from a programming language
feature point of view, can we point out
a couple of really cool features that
many or most scripting languages today
have? Also very very difficult point
because they are pretty different. You
have
scripting languages that come from a non
OO background and right now are moving
to an OO background or getting OO
languages
and there are pure object-oriented
languages like Ruby which
are really designed to be
object-oriented from core on. So
scripting languages are of course very
very very different. So everything I
right now say
you find counterexamples for anything.
Okay. Nevertheless, most of them have
regular expression embedded in the
language.
You remember they they come from this
shell replacement
thing and background and there you have
to do a lot of things with strings and
so on. So regular expressions and easy
string handling easy handling of data
structure structures like arrays or hash
tables are very important things.
They are
in any scripting language right now.
What they also do have is automatic
memory management. They have garbage
collection built in to make it easier as
I said before. So to program you have
don't have to deal with all this
technical stuff there. You just program
in the problem domain.
They're usually very open to use other
programs to to start other processes to
stop them communicate with them. So they
are usually integrated in the
environment or the
operation
that that's
maybe also a consequence of history
where scripting languages were often
used to glue together building blocks
that have been built in in other
languages.
Yeah,
exactly. Some have a lot of
yeah more functional flavor something
like high order functions functions as
objects or closures.
This is also point of the
easy to program thing. So
a lot of advanced features in there but
but not so equally spread between them.
They have different concepts there. They
often have powerful reflective features
um
to dynamically build programs to to
yeah you can as they are usually
interpreted you of course can
expand or extend the program by the
program itself easily.
So that means you can you can write code
that dynamically builds classes. Like
for example, you can ask your user you
know
give me the attributes of your data
structure you want to have and then you
build an algorithm that dynamically
builds a data structure that has those
attributes. Exactly.
Of course with Java or C# you can do all
this too but it's
a lot easier to do it with scripting
languages. Right because in Java you
would have to do it on bytecode level
and that that's that's no no no not very
fun. It's not easy. Yeah. No. But but I
think I think we'll have separate
episodes for
functional languages and also
on on on reflection because that's
that's that are those are huge topics
that that we cannot you know like
discuss today. Yeah. One thing that
already that almost has religious
discussions about it is the discussion
about strong typing. People say yeah, we
need strong typing otherwise the
compiler can't tell me you know all
those kinds of bugs. What do you think
about that? How important is strong
typing and static typing? Typing before
runtime. Well actually
this is almost a religious topic.
You find strong proponents on both
sides.
I guess it's it's very
and very complicated topic and I think
we should do another episode on this to
to go deeper into detail there because
it's not that easy to differentiate
between dynamic typing and static
typing.
A lot of
points to discuss.
My personal opinion is you don't have to
have static typing actually.
Static type checking by the compiler is
is a useful thing
and
helps a lot. Nevertheless, you can write
you you you have to pay a price for it.
You can't just send them
yeah message call a function send a
message is the more dynamic way of it.
Send a message to any object you want
and the object decides if it can handle
the the message or if it doesn't. So you
can do a lot of cool things with dynamic
typing actually.
But it it comes with a price. You have
to do more unit tests. You have to check
a lot things that the compiler checks
usually for you in the static type
languages.
That that's one of the points that makes
it really difficult to use scripting
languages in huge teams actually. You
have to use discipline instead of well
technical or language feature.
Many people say that if you write
the right amount of of unit tests like
those you know test first folks.
They say that if you do that then you
will catch all the typing problems also.
So that means if if you use Java
and you write so many unit tests that
you cover all your functional
requirements then this would also catch
all the typing
problems. So that means that you you in
in in languages like Java
you don't have the advantages of dynamic
typing but you you
the advantage of the compiler catching
the static typing problems don't really
pay off because you would catch those
problems also if you wrote so many unit
tests as as necessary to to to test your
functional Absolutely my opinion. The
only problem I have with this is
usually people don't write enough unit
tests. So
it's more a theoretical point I guess.
If you would yes, absolutely and I think
it's it's the better way actually
because then you not only have your your
typing problems fixed but also your
semantic problems fixed. So doing the
right amount of unit tests is the real
solution. But if I look at the projects
I see all over the world right now,
they don't have enough unit tests. So
having a compiler that helps there
additionally is not a bad thing
actually.
Right. Okay. So One additional point
there. If you look at the next version
of C# for example,
they move to yeah not really dynamic
typing but they they you don't have to
declare what type of variable you have.
The compiler figures out in in the
well while compiling. So
the the static type languages also move
a bit more to the dynamic type
languages. Still there's a huge
difference in
nevertheless it's they they move in this
direction right now.
Yeah, I think C# 3.0 is a really really
good example of how
kind of classical languages like C# or
Java kind of move into the direction of
of
into a domain where typically dynamic
languages have been like with with kind
of automatic typing with language
integrated query with with closures and
all these things. I actually will try to
get some Microsoft person on on the
podcast to to talk about that because I
think that's really fascinating.
Yeah and on the other hand of
it's a huge misconception that scripting
languages don't have type checking at
all. They do type check. All the
variables have types. You just handle it
in a different way. So it
checks at runtime and it's different.
Yeah.
But as I said
this this dynamic versus static typing
thing is a huge thing. I guess we should
really do an
other episode on it. I I took a note for
that. So we'll do that at some point.
Okay, so
can you maybe list
a number of typically used scripting
languages and maybe
point out on a very high level view that
they're the most important features?
Yeah, of course.
First that comes in mind of course is
Pearl. I
think it's still the the most used. I'm
not sure. I have no statistic but but it
seems
like that.
Pearl is grandmother of the modern
scripting languages I guess.
Very strong or at least at the point of
time when it was invented very strong on
this regular expression stuff which also
brought it a bad image because a lot of
people wrote code Pearl code that was
ugly and almost impossible to read
which doesn't have to be like that of
course
but
well
a lot of people have mixed feelings on
Pearl.
Nevertheless, the most important I would
say or the the the hugest scripting
language at least still.
Python
came up to be very clean by design. One
interesting point at Python and most
discussed while
not so important actually is they have
semantic white spaces
like in the the early COBOL versions
where it does matter where you write
something how many spaces are in there.
This is a point where a lot of
discussion is going on.
So
I I love a bit about it because it's
it's funny to to see this little feature
so
hot discussed by different people.
Of course you don't need the curly
braces, right?
Yeah. Yeah. I once tried to generate
Python and so you have to generate all
the semantic white space and that's
really a pain. Oh yeah. Yeah, I could
imagine that's not easy.
Python has a huge library.
A lot of stuff you can use out of the
library.
Next language that comes to mind right
now because it has a lot of um noise
around
is Ruby. Ruby um is a purely or with a
design goal to be purely object-oriented
and it actually is. It's it's very
beautiful implementation of object
orientation in my opinion.
Uh very nice little language.
Huge in Japan. Actually, it's the most
used scripting language in Japan where
it comes from, I guess. Or plays too.
Very very um popular there. Has a lot of
noise generated with the Ruby on Rails
framework or solution Mhm. uh right now.
Very very nice language. Um I would
recommend to look into it. It's it's
interesting to learn it.
All the meta programming concepts are
very very nice implemented. But I think
when we do the uh the episode on
reflection and meta programming, we'll
do this based on Ruby.
Yeah.
Good idea. Next language that comes to
my mind is Groovy. Um
why Groovy on this list? Uh because I
come from a Java background. I I done a
lot of Java things. So uh Groovy is
basically um
a mixture of the the best of features of
most um scripting languages. Uh has a
lot of Ruby flavor
um but runs on the virtual machine,
which is a huge difference.
So um
still in in Yeah, well, it's it's not
done right now still. Um
it's it's going to grow. It it's has to
stabilize still.
Um but very interesting language and
concept, too. If you don't need
something you you use right now in a
huge project, look into Groovy if you
are in the Java world, of course. So
very interesting language, too.
So to summarize, Pearl is very good in
string handling. Python is more or less
a functional language with with OO
concepts added. Ruby is an OO language
with some functional concepts added. And
the big point of Groovy is certainly its
Java integration. And actually, Pearl is
not only good of on string handling, of
course. It it's
Yeah, but that's what's traditionally
used.
And also, many people say that
um you you shouldn't kind of really
compare Pearl with Python, Ruby, and
Groovy because Python, Ruby, and Groovy
are more really more modern languages
where people
looked at how you can cleanly implement
functional or object-oriented
programming, whereas Pearl is more or
less a mix of useful features, but not a
real nice feel to it.
Yeah.
Because uh or um of course, this is um
a lot of taste comes there. It's also
I don't
I don't think we can say one is better
than the other. Just look at them and
you will see what fits your
uh wishes best.
One topic that we didn't discuss yet,
but that's important is What is What
What about IDE support? Are there any,
you know, Eclipse for Ruby? Yeah. Uh
well, actually, that's This is a weak
point of scripting languages in my
opinion.
Um
there are plugins for Eclipse for for a
different uh scripting languages
actually, but they are basically um text
editors with syntax highlighting. So
it's not very strong IDE support for
scripting languages right now.
Um This
One of the reasons is actually this
static versus dynamic typing thing.
Um
it's it's hard to for an IDE to figure
out um what are the types of the
variables you deal with because because
they simply are not defined at the time
you write it. They are defined at
runtime. So it's pretty hard to write
something
um that
Yeah, can do advanced stuff like
refactoring, for example. Actually, you
can do if you look the original
refactoring browser was done in
Smalltalk.
Yes. It's different. It's very
different.
Uh I don't know how deep we should dive
into this uh how they are implemented.
They they are they are pretty different.
I mean, if you you have a refactoring
browser for Java, the the IDE actually
knows what type it has to deal with and
where it will be called or where a
method will be called and all this
stuff.
Uh the Smalltalk refactoring browser um
used a different concept. It actually
replaced code
and at runtime um you can, for example,
into a dummy version of the function you
call of the method you call, and uh this
will do refactoring or complete the
refactoring at runtime. So it's it's
very very different concept. Okay.
Okay, so so so that means today IDE
support for today's scripting languages
is isn't as good as you would as what
you know from Java.
Exactly. Yeah.
So that there are IDEs like ActiveState
or Script Solutions from ActiveState.
Yeah, but but if you're used to to Java
Yeah, it's it's different. It feels
really really different. But you can do
debugging in your IDE. You have syntax
highlighting and all this stuff, but um
that's almost all of the features you
get. Right. Um so what should our
listeners do if they want to dig deeper
because our time is already more or less
up? Okay.
First thing,
of course, is to choose your language.
Um there's a lot of information on the
web. I guess we will
add a few links to our website where you
can check
Show notes, yeah. starting points to to
get a bit deeper feeling how they how
the languages feel, what are the key
features, and what's the philosophy
behind them. So um I would say you have
to choose your favorite language, which
is easy, I guess, because they are
pretty different languages. Okay. And
then um just use the web pages. There's
a lot of information on the web because
most of the scripting languages are
actually
open source languages, some kind of open
source. So um
most of the information actually is on
the web. And of course, there are a lot
of good books, but
um start with the web.
We'll we'll put a couple of things into
the show notes, and you can start from
there.
Yeah.
Okay. Anything else you want to say
about scripting languages that you
really want to
our listeners to know about? Actually, I
I think we have touched the most
important points uh in the discussion.
So Okay. just take a look at them. I
think scripting languages will get huge
or are huge actually, if you look at the
the distribution of languages right now.
They become more and more important, and
I think we will see a lot of influence
of scripting languages in the future on
the non-scripting languages as well. So
having a
um an understanding a good understanding
of scripting languages will help you a
lot in the next years.
And we promise that we'll bring further
episodes down the road um on on specific
topics such as dynamic typing or
reflection or all these kinds of things.
Okay.
So, thanks. Thank you.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio. For general
information, feedback, and past
episodes, go to se-radio.net.
Software Engineering Radio wants to
thank Henning Pauly for providing the
music we use in this show.